hello all thank you for your support and
interest
we've reached 250 patrons on the patreon
account which makes you early adopters
the landscape of ideas to be covered is
complicated but I think I found a way to
do this so that it will be intuitive for
those with little prior exposure to this
kind of thinking you'll start seeing
that soon number of people have
expressed an interest in continuing
developments in the evergreen story in
an effort not to pollute the science
with a necessary controversy I will
provide those updates in a separate
playlist on the YouTube channel but be
prepared evolutionary biology especially
as it approaches humans is in no way
politically correct this is not a safe
space and there will be no taboos that
said some of what I am interested in
doing is understanding the evolutionary
basis for unconscionable human behavior
so that we might eliminate them in the
future this is a thank you video I'm
going to take this opportunity to talk
about a little piece of related material
the evolutionary basis of gratitude what
I present here is formally speaking a
hypothesis it is in fact the very first
lesson that I taught to my first
students at Evergreen and everything
I've seen since is consistent with it
let's take on four related concepts
gratitude guilt indignation and apology
gratitude is the expression of an
honorable debt I thank you right now for
coming along with me on this journey you
have agreed to support this channel and
are making it possible for me to bring
this evolutionary material to a larger
audience which I have long wanted to do
I am indebted to you for your support
guilt is the imposition of a debt on
oneself which is experienced as shame
indignation is like an invoice here is a
debt that you have yet to recognize
apology is slightly more complex it
contains an expression of indebtedness
that can be cashed in and is also a
communication of awareness of the
specific nature of the harm done by
conveying that I know what I did wrong
the apologizer also increases the cost
of themselves if they engage in the same
thing in the future an apology is thus a
kind of insurance against the same
behavior repeating itself once you start
thinking about apologies this way it is
interesting to watch the tiny debts that
cause most apologies and the release
from debt the general
follows you bump into somebody you say
I'm very sorry and they say there's no
problem or it was my fault it is also
interesting to recognize the effects of
in sincere apologies an insincere
apology exacerbates the harm done if
somebody says for example I'm very sorry
that you felt hurt by what I said they
are not acknowledging that they said
something hurtful a sincere apology on
the other hand mitigates harm
so in summary gratitude guilt
indignation and apology gratitude is an
expression of honorable debt guilt is
the imposition of a debt on oneself
which is experienced a shame and likely
leads to an apology indignation is an
invoice here is a debt that you have yet
to recognize apology is both an
expression of indebtedness and a
protection to those harmed against
suffering similar harm in the future I
am grateful to you all for joining this
effort and for being early adopters
there is so much to be on earth welcome